<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Enquiry into the ministry of Presbyterians, whether lawful or not? as also into their way of preaching : in a letter to a Presbyterian minister of the kirk.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 91 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45907</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12820436</idno>
  <idno type="VID">94200</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240961108</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing I217</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9037</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12820436</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45907)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94200)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 385:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Enquiry into the ministry of Presbyterians, whether lawful or not? as also into their way of preaching : in a letter to a Presbyterian minister of the kirk.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[8], 174 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for B. Tooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata on p. [1].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Presbyterian Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:94200:1"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 35. <hi>lin.</hi> 18. <hi>read</hi> eighth's, <hi>p.</hi> 38. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>r.</hi> Bishops. <hi>p.</hi> 65. <hi>l.</hi> 7 <hi>r.</hi> or to conclude, that. <hi>p.</hi> 66. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>r.</hi> Sacrament. <hi>p.</hi> 69. <hi>l.</hi> 19. <hi>r.</hi> and that they are. <hi>p.</hi> 158. <hi>l.</hi> 18. <hi>r.</hi> that are. <hi>p.</hi> 163. <hi>l.</hi> 17. <hi>r.</hi> Scripture. <hi>p.</hi> 70. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>r.</hi> numerous.</p>
            <p>Other litteral faults, and mistoppings the Reader is desired to correct at his leisure.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94200:1"/>
            <p>AN ENQUIRY INTO <hi>The Ministry of</hi> PRESBYTERIANS, Whether Lawful or not? AS ALSO Into their way of PREACHING; IN A LETTER TO A <hi>Presbyterian Minister</hi> OF THE KIRK.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Second Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>B. Tooke,</hi> at the <hi>Ship</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1678.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:94200:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94200:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is not now the <hi>Order</hi> or <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter</hi> of the <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy,</hi> nor their power of Binding and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solving Sinners, nor Catechism, nor yet the Liturgy of the Church, which the <hi>Multitude</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:94200:3"/>have any great regard for, but only their Lungs and Faculties of Preaching. By this Curiosity after <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> it comes to pass, that the <hi>People</hi> are inveigled away by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very new Light and Impostor in Religion, who is commonly a Zealous and Popular <hi>Preacher;</hi> who wants no good words, nor
<pb facs="tcp:94200:3"/>
               <hi>Scripture</hi> - Phrases, nor demure converse. And so profound a <hi>Jugler</hi> he usually is, that we are not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise able to detect him, than by enquiring in to his <hi>Mission.</hi> The on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yl way for the <hi>Clergy</hi> (say some grave-beard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed People) is to study to out-preach these <hi>Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors:</hi> But I pray a little of their grave
<pb facs="tcp:94200:4"/>advice, how it shall be done, whether in <hi>words</hi> or <hi>sence?</hi> In <hi>words,</hi> is impossible: if in <hi>sence,</hi> it hath been done long enough ago.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94200:4"/>
            <head>A LETTER TO A <hi>Presbyterian Minister,</hi> Concerning his Mission, or Authority to Preach the Gospel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Should be very much obliged to receive a Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from you, which I could never give my self, concerning the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94200:5"/>Validity of your Presbyterian <hi>Missi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> I conceive it to be the most material thing in difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us, and that it ought to be consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the first place: There being no Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posture like that of as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suming to be Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Gospel, without Lawful <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</hi> I shall here
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94200:5"/>trouble you with the Reasons of my dissa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>First then, I must crave your Pardon to look backward, as far as your first reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Ancestors,</hi> (from whom Presbitery does more immediately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive it self) Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> in <hi>Geneva,</hi> Mr. <hi>Knox</hi> in <hi>Scotland, &amp;c.</hi> And
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94200:6"/>then permit me to ask a certain Question, which hitherto none of you would do us the favour to resolve; who sent them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the <hi>World?</hi> that is, in your sence, to Preach the Gospel? and <hi>How should they Preach, except they were sent? Rom.</hi> 10.15. Which words of St. <hi>Paul</hi> seem to be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94200:6"/>a Question, but are indeed a full and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory Affirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that no Abilities whatsoever can qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie any Persons for Preachers of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, without external and lawful <hi>Mission.</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> though ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the Apostle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship by an immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Call from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, must not enter
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94200:7"/>on his Office, without License and Impositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the hands of the <hi>Church, Acts</hi> 13.3.</p>
            <p>This being so evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that lawful <hi>Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion</hi> is essential to a Preacher of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and so confest by your party; it will not a little concern you to be well assured, that your Ancestors of the <hi>Kirk,</hi> (those Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94200:7"/>of the World) wanted not this <hi>essen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial;</hi> nor consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly your self, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive your <hi>Ministry</hi> from them.</p>
            <p>Grant me (Sir) a little of your pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and consider there are only these Five imaginable Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities, from whence they could pretend to have received it.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94200:8"/>1. The Spirit of God. 2ly. Themselves, or their own internal Spirit. 3ly. Or the People. 4ly. Christ and his Apostles. 5ly. Or the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Other <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> or <hi>Mission,</hi> (as namely that of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church) you will not pretend to.</p>
            <p>And first, That they were raised up
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94200:8"/>by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God, is (you know) the matter in <hi>Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie,</hi> and the Allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all Fanaticks; it will be therefore a reasonable demand, by what evidences did it appear to the World? And how shall the Contemners of your Gospel be left unexcusable, but by evidence of their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94200:9"/>Authority, who are sent to reveal it? In the Affairs of this World, <hi>Ambassadors</hi> (you know) must not want their <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentials:</hi> How much less the Ambassadors of <hi>Religion?</hi> What? To reform the <hi>World,</hi> over-run with Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and Superstition, and no appearance of your <hi>Authority,</hi> for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94200:9"/>so doing! To this you Answer, That the powerful gifts and fanctity of those Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons were great tokens of their being inspired by the Spirit of God; and that the conversi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of many thousands from Superstition to Godliness was an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted <hi>Seal</hi> to their Ministry. This is the Answer of all Dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94200:10"/>and Parties of what name soever, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents, Anaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists, Behemists,</hi> &amp;c. That they easily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands, no body denies; but whether from Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstition to godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, or only to a Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risaical pride, censori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness and contempt of their <hi>Neighbours,</hi> is the great <hi>Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie.</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:94200:10"/>Nay, was it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver made a Note of a man Converted (as the excellent <hi>Friendly debate</hi> observes) that, though he have a great many faults, yet he is wrought to an antipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to Bishops, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-prayer, and Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice? And as to your self, I might appeal to your Conscience, whether you esteem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94200:11"/>man a right <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert,</hi> that is, a Friend to these things; as to those powerful gifts you speak of, you do not mean any thing that is <hi>miraculous,</hi> or that others (perhaps <hi>Socinians</hi> themselves) will not as soon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to, whether pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or preaching; and truly, as for the sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of your whole <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:94200:11"/>observable is the confession of Mr. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> himself, in his Comment on the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty fourth Verse of the eleventh Chapter of <hi>Daniel;</hi> and I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise you not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure him in the quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Sed in illorum exiguo numero qui sese ab Idololatriis Papa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus subduxerunt, major Pars plena est perfidia
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94200:12"/>&amp; dolis; praeclarum quidem Zelum simu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, sed si intus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutias, reperies ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos esse fraudibus.</hi> Of that small number of Persons (saith he) who profess the pure Gospel, the greater part is full of perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness and deceit: They pretend an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Zeal; but if you inspect them nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94200:12"/>you shall find them abounding with Frauds.</p>
            <p>If such were the first fruits of your <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> in the days of <hi>Calvin,</hi> what may we expect now? Not but that others may be as faulty: but this, methinks, is such a <hi>Character,</hi> as one would not expect in so Reformed and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94200:13"/>so <hi>Godly</hi> a Party.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves,</hi> or their own internal Spirit. It is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surd: For so all men may become Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Gospel, that will assume the Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> let us allow this Authority for good; and then, I pray, will not <hi>Socinians, Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94200:13"/>Anabaptists, Behemists, Fift-Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy-men,</hi> (and who not?) enter in at this Door, and plead their Call by the <hi>People,</hi> to reform the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians?</hi> Or have they not done it <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready?</hi> Be pleased to tell us what People do you mean? If those of your own o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, they will not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94200:14"/>in some places a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to a Fourth, or Fifth part of the People: And must all the rest be debar'd from Electing their own Preachers? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides (you know) it is not the People's <hi>Call</hi> alone, that can constitute a Preacher of the Gospel: It is the <hi>Mission,</hi> and <hi>Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of your Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94200:14"/>that I am now enquiring after; you cannot be ignorant concerning the Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Election, or Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for Ministers, that it had been dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us'd many Centuries before <hi>Calvin,</hi> for the Tumults, Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and confusions that attended it: The unstable <hi>People</hi> sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or never agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94200:15"/>about the Persons to be Elected. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> himself is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, whom the People of <hi>Geneva</hi> Elected to be their Teacher; but after a while expel'd him their Town, and after that invited him in again; as <hi>Beza</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates it. Shew us any Divine precept, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vesting the <hi>People</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:94200:15"/>with Authority to chuse their several <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors,</hi> and you will very much oblige not only your own Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but all the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sects this day ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in the Christian World. If by the People's <hi>Call</hi> you only mean their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, our Ministers want it not; for if the People have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94200:16"/>thing material to object, our <hi>Canons</hi> provide Suspension and Deprivation; if not, their displeasure signifies nothing. The <hi>Scripture</hi> mentions not any Popular E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, but of Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons only; because they were to be the dispensers of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple's Charity, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.3.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:94200:16"/>
            <p>Fourthly, Or will you derive your <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry</hi> from Christ and his Apostles? But all dissenters Proclaim their extraction from the same Original: which of them shall we believe? From Christ and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles? Give me leave to ask whether imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately or mediately? Immediately you will
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94200:17"/>not say; if mediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I pray inform us by whom, or from whose <hi>hands</hi> did your <hi>Puritan</hi> Ancestors re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their <hi>Mission,</hi> or <hi>Ordination?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, in the first place, some Body must send them to preach the Gospel. Was it the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> Yes, I have heard you say: And
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94200:17"/>is not this to confess your selves the Emis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> that <hi>Man</hi> of sin, the <hi>Whore</hi> of <hi>Babylon? Quid Christo cum</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial? But the unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness of it is, that this <hi>Mission</hi> from <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Roman</hi> Bishops, will as soon Authorise the Sermons of a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish <hi>Fryar,</hi> as those of your <hi>Predeces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors.</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:94200:18"/>And as to your pretended Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from <hi>Rome,</hi> there is one difficulty in it, that I confess I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not resolve; was it not <hi>Praelatical Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> if any, they received from that Church? And was such Ordination good and valid, yea or no? If good, by what <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> do you take
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94200:18"/>upon you to abolish it, together with the whole <hi>Order</hi> of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops? If not valid, what will become of your Orders? Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal imposition of hands we receive from Bishops, as a <hi>power</hi> Superiour to <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters:</hi> and to allow it for good, is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess the impertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of that <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:94200:19"/>Ordination you would set up in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to it. And further, I would glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly understand, are any Persons sent to go and preach the Gospel after their own <hi>sence?</hi> After their own <hi>Conscience</hi> as you call it? If so, then he that hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd <hi>Mission</hi> from your <hi>Kirk,</hi> may when
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:94200:19"/>he list, become an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent,</hi> or <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptist</hi> Preacher, and justify his new Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine by your <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for <hi>Calvin,</hi> I have read over his life, written by <hi>Beza;</hi> and I find he was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly design'd for the Church by his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, but never actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally initiated in any
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:94200:20"/>Orders of the <hi>Roman Church: Nullis Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificiis Ordinibus ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiatus,</hi> are <hi>Beza</hi>'s words; who being his great Acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and Successor at <hi>Geneva,</hi> could not but know it very well. I was of opinion that your Founder <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> had been in some <hi>Orders,</hi> until your own <hi>Beza</hi> informed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:94200:20"/>me to the contrary. He came to <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za.</hi>
               </note> in the Year 1536. And at first, (though intreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the People of that City) would not consent to become their Preacher, but only Professor of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity; as being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scious of his want of <hi>Orders.</hi> If any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers do Affirm, that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:94200:21"/>
               <hi>Calvin</hi> was a Priest of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church (as I think they do not) doubtless his friend <hi>Beza</hi> knew it better; to whom as also to <hi>Papirius Mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonius,</hi> another wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Calvin</hi>'s life, I must refer the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for further Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. This I grant, that the Bishop of <hi>Noyon</hi> in <hi>Picardy,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:94200:21"/>gave him the profits of a small Benefice or two, to support him in his Studies at <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris;</hi> which at his return from thence he made no scruple to sell; and went his way to <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we need not trouble our selves: The matter is confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by <hi>Calvin</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:94200:22"/>in his Epistle to the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> dated <hi>December</hi> 4th. 1554. to do him right, I must desire the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders leave to set down his words at length.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Si promiscue fas non est,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>See the Volum of his Epistles Printed at</hi> Geneva, 1575.</note> quos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis ad Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storum munus ascende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, rite eos vocari &amp; institui necesse est, qui se probare volent legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:94200:22"/>&amp; honore dignos. Fateor, optandum es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>set ut valeret continua successio, ut Functio ipsa quasi per manus traderetur. Sed me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moria tenendum est quod prius attigi, quum Ecclesiae anima sit doctrinae puritas, fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stra quae Ecclesiae pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priasunt, &amp; ab integro ejus statu dependent, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud eos homines requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:94200:23"/>quos constat es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se professos Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lii hostes; quia au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Papae tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de abrupta fuit ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Ordinationis se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, novo subsidio nunc opus est ad Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiae instaurationem. Atque omnino extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarium fuit hoc munus quod dominus nobis injunxit, dum opera nostra ad colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendas
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:94200:23"/>Ecclesias usus est.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qui ergo ita prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter spem hominum insolito modo repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te apparuerunt, eor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um vocatio a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muni regula aestima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri non debet.</hi> Here the Reader will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve in the first place, how he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesses the necessity of lawful Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:94200:24"/>that it is not for every man to take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the office of a Preacher in Gods Church. I confess (saith he,) it were to be wished that the Chain of Succession might take place; but this cannot be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted together with the purity of Doctrine, from those (meaning the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>)
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:94200:24"/>who are professed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to the Gospel. The true line there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of <hi>Ordination</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing broken off (mark this;) through the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of the <hi>Pope,</hi> this Office which the Lord hath enjoyned us for the gathering of new Churches, was wholly extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is a confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:94200:25"/>plain enough of his want of ordinary <hi>Mission. Farellus</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so and <hi>Viret</hi> his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Preachers at <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva,</hi> you will find in the same <hi>Querpo</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Orders. As for <hi>John Knox,</hi> he was (saith Mr. <hi>Samuel Clark,</hi> a Presbyterian Minister who writes his life) put into Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders very young; that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:94200:25"/>is, when he was Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessedly of the Popish Religion, he was made Deacon or Priest of that Church by Episcopal Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Let us believe this on the credit of Mr. <hi>Clark:</hi> And still we are to seek for their Presbyterian <hi>Mission;</hi> their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority (I mean) for obtruding on the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:94200:26"/>World their Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Doctrine and Discipline. This (Sir) I doubt you will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be able to shew.</p>
            <p>Besides, I cannot find that any of the first <hi>Reformers</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi> (except <hi>Knox</hi>) could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to any Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at all; in which particular you are greatly concern'd to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:94200:26"/>satisfie the World; since you grant, a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle <hi>Presbyter</hi> cannot confer Orders.</p>
            <p>Indeed the Church of <hi>England</hi> is so ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensive of your want of true Orders, that she admits none of you to her Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical Functions without <hi>Reordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Presbyteri &amp; Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aconi
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:94200:27"/>praeter Episco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum nihil agere per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentent,</hi> Saith the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth <hi>Canon</hi> of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles; a <hi>Canon</hi> w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> though it were not <hi>Apostolical,</hi> you cannot deny to be very ancient: And do not Saint <hi>Austin</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius</hi> rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon it among the Heresies of <hi>Aerius,</hi> that he affirmed,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:94200:27"/>Bishop and Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter were the same thing? <hi>Aerius cum esset Presbyter</hi> (saith St. <hi>Austin,) doluisse fertur, quod Episco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus non potuit Ordinari,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Haeres.</hi> 53.</note> &amp;c. <hi>Aerius,</hi> being a Presbyter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented his disappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Bishoprick, and to satisfie his humour of revenge, would needs assert
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:94200:28"/>that they are the same Office. Yea, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is evidently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst your Parity of Ministers; for doth not St. <hi>Paul</hi> advise <hi>Timothy</hi> how to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise his Authority over <hi>Presbyters,</hi> say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Receive not an Accusation against a Presbyter, but under two or three Witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses?</hi> 1 Tim. 5.19.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:94200:28"/>and again, <hi>Lay hands suddenly on no man.</hi> And was not <hi>Titus,</hi> a single person, invested with the power of Ordination? <hi>For this cause left I thee in</hi> Greet, <hi>that thou shouldst set in order the things that are wanting,</hi> (the Greek word signifies to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul or correct) <hi>and ordain Elders in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:94200:29"/>City as I had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed thee,</hi> Tit. 1.5. Thus I am satisfied your Presbyterian <hi>Progenitors</hi> had no ordinary Mission at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sleidan,</hi> a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Historian, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports in his Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries,
<note place="margin">Comment. lib. 5. ad annum 1525.</note> that <hi>Luther</hi> hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Multitudes assembled
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:94200:29"/>by <hi>Thomas Muncer,</hi> the famous Prophet of the Anabaptists, wrote an Epistle to the Magistrates of <hi>Mulhusen,</hi> a City in <hi>Germany,</hi> (where the said <hi>Muncer</hi> remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) advising them to require of him, who sent him to reform the world? and if he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, God, that he evidence it by some
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:94200:30"/>sign or extraordinary Token; otherwise that he be rejected: <hi>hoc enim proprium &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliare est Deo</hi> (said Luther) <hi>ut quoties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suetam &amp; ordinariam viam velit immutari, tum voluntatem suam aliquo signo declaret.</hi> This is proper and familiar to God, whensoever he would change the establisht
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:94200:30"/>and ordinary way of Religion, to manifest his pleasure by some Token or other.</p>
            <p>The same <hi>Quaere</hi> (Sir) you may at your leisure do us the favour to resolve in reference to your self. You cannot, alas! pretend any necessity to reform Episcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, but all the other Sects will plead the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:94200:31"/>same to reform you. Yes, the <hi>Independents</hi> and <hi>Anabaptists</hi> have already revenged our Cause; and you may remember the time when they supplanted your Party, by the same <hi>Mission,</hi> that you reformed us, namely the <hi>Sword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor will it relieve you to say, that by this Argument the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:94200:31"/>
               <hi>Jewish</hi> Church reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Christ and his Apostles; the case not being the same be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Christ and the <hi>Jewish</hi> Church, and between us and you. To satisfie the <hi>Jews</hi> and their Question, <hi>By what Authority doest thou these things?</hi> our blessed Saviour appeals to the Miracles which he
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:94200:32"/>wrought, <hi>If ye believe not me, believe the works which I do.</hi> Nor will it avail you to return the <hi>Quaere</hi> upon our selves, Who sent us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> This truly is no Answer, but a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siring us to answer for you: Be pleased to know then, that the Church of <hi>England</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:94200:32"/>was never of your froward and uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable humour in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to that Church; that she pretends to no power of reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Church of <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Spain,</hi> or <hi>France.</hi> To reform our selves (saith Mr.
<note place="margin">Eccles. Pol. lib. 3. sect. 1.</note>
               <hi>Hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi>) is not to sever from the Church we were of before; we are very sensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:94200:33"/>of their errors; and yet we confess with Saint <hi>Austin,</hi> there is no just neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity to divide the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Catholick Church; because se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations in the Church tend to no other end, but to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit the Christian Religion, and render it less considerable, if not contemptible to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:94200:33"/>its Adversaries, <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Infidels.</hi> He that will admit no Church (saith Primate <hi>Bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall</hi>) but that which is spotless, with <hi>Ace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sius,</hi> must provide a Ladder for himself to climb alone to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <p>But as to your Party (Sir) still the question remains. Who gave them Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:94200:34"/>to preach their Reformation to these Kingdoms? give me leave to observe to you this passage in the <hi>Racovian</hi> Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chism: there I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the question is put, <hi>Nonne ij qui do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent in Ecclesia</hi> (So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciniana) <hi>ut singulari aliqua ratione mittan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, opus habent?</hi> Whether the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:94200:34"/>of <hi>Socinian</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine have need of any extraordinary <hi>Mission?</hi> the Answer is <hi>Nullo modo, quia nullam novam, nec in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auditam afferunt do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinam, &amp;c.</hi> That is, not at all, because <hi>Socinians</hi> preach no new nor strange do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin, but that onely which is primitive and declared in the holy
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:94200:35"/>Scriptures. The same is affirmed by Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> concerning his own Reformation in the Preface to his <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutions:</hi> which the <hi>Lutherans</hi> (you know) will by no means admit for truth. See <hi>Conradus Schluselburg de The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologia Calvinistarum;</hi> as if <hi>Independents, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians,</hi> and all the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:94200:35"/>Sects that ever mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted the Church, did not press as much for themselves, boasting of Gospel-truth.</p>
            <p>The Question at present is not, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your <hi>Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Sermons be the doctrin of the holy Scriptures? but the question is, what Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority you have to preach them? and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:94200:36"/>who gave you the Authority?</p>
            <p>To say that your Party agree with us in all the Vital Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Religion, is to say what, perhaps, few of you believe: for I doubt not, (if opportunity serv'd) every Sect of you would advance its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spective Religion, as if that onely were
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:94200:36"/>Gospel, and all other but lies and supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition: or if you do believe it, the more is your unhappiness to molest the world about opinions, which you do not esteem of any vital impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>I wish I could ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige you to consider, whether you ought to take upon you to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:94200:37"/>Reform, that is, sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press the Universal Order of Christs Church by Bishops, &amp;c. banish all ancient Liturgies, the use of the Creed, the Lords Prayer, and Ten Commandments out of your Publick De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions; all Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versary Solemnities of Christs Nativity, Resurrection, &amp;c. all
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:94200:37"/>Reverence or Kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Christs Body and Blood; revile the <hi>Church</hi> (whereof I cannot say you, but your Ancestors were made Members by Baptism) with the names of Superstition and Idolatry: preach your desperate do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin of absolute Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, and the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:94200:38"/>impossibility of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; introduce your own extemporary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions instead of Liturgy; levy war a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst your Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign; and all this without any Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity!</p>
            <p>For all these strange things I should think (Sir) your Ancestors had but need of some
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:94200:38"/>extrordinary <hi>Mission.</hi> Perhaps you will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer and tell us, that your <hi>Mission</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, and that extraordinary Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets have been sent into the world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Miracles, as <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptist;</hi> yea fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that Miracles are no certain eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of true Prophets.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>John</hi> the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:94200:39"/>
               <hi>Baptist,</hi> you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the words of the <hi>Angel, Luke</hi> 2.15. he was filled with the Holy Ghost from his Mothers womb: he shall go before in the spirit and power of <hi>Elias,</hi> (a Character to which your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren will not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend) he was a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son prophesied of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ages before his
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:94200:39"/>birth, <hi>Isaiah</hi> 40.3. <hi>The voice of one cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Wilderness, make strait the way of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Again (say you) Miracles are no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain evidences of true Prophets, because <hi>there shall arise false Christs and false Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, who shall shew great signs and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; insomuch that
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:94200:40"/>if it were possible, they shall deceive the very Elect. Wherefore if they shall say unto you, behold he is in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sart, go not forth; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold he is in the secret Chambers, believe it not,</hi> Mat. 24.26.</p>
            <p>That false Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets can work any Miracle but <hi>deceptio visus,</hi> I do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve. The meaning of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:94200:40"/>our Saviours words is this; if any other Prophet after him shall arise, assuming to be that Christ or Messias sent from God, though he may pretend to strange things, believe him not, go not forth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him. If new Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets (Sir) though they come with a shew of Miracles, are
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:94200:41"/>to be suspected, must we presently receive all the Preachers of new Lights, that have not so much as the pretence?</p>
            <p>I find a late Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter asserting that in holy Scripture there be two marks, by which together, not asunder, a true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, or one newly sent from God, is to
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:94200:41"/>be known; one is, the doing of Miracles; the other is, the not teaching any doctrin of Morality adverse to that which hath been already taught of old: asunder (he saith) neither of these is sufficient; and for proof alledgeth two places of Scripture, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.1, 2, <hi>&amp;</hi> 3 verses compared with
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:94200:42"/>
               <hi>Matt.</hi> 24.24. Our blessed Saviour and his Apostles fulfilled both these marks; first in their Miracles, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.22. 2<seg rend="sup">ly.</seg> they taught no doctrin of Morality opposite to that which they found already established. <hi>Christ came not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy the Law, but to fulfil it, saying none other things than
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:94200:42"/>what Moses and the Prophets did say should come to pass.</hi> But he preached a doctrin that had all the obliging chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of Vertue and Goodness, of respect to Order and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, witness his admirable Sermon on the Mount; <hi>non vox hominem sonat:</hi> Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness his advice to the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:94200:43"/>Multitude and to his Disciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.1. <hi>The Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risees sit in Moses seat; all therefore whatsoever they bid you observe, that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve and do.</hi> Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (I say) his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon on the Mount, where he presses the necessity of moral goodness, and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:94200:43"/>of God; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise methinks then your Prophet <hi>Calvin</hi> hath done. I shall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance a remarkable place in the second book of his Instituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the 7th Chapter and fifth Section. <hi>Quod autem impossibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem legis observatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem diximus, id nunc paucis verbis expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candum simul &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmandum.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:94200:44"/>Solet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim vulgo absurdissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma sententia videri, ut</hi> Jeronimus <hi>non du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitavit Anathema illi denunciare; at quid</hi> Jeronimo <hi>visum sit, nihil moror. Impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile appello quod nec fuit unquam, &amp; ne in posterum sit, Dei de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creto &amp; ordinatione impeditur.</hi> I shall now (saith he) explain and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:94200:44"/>confirm what I have said of the impossibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to observe the Commandments; w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> commonly seems a very absurd asserti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, insomuch that <hi>Jerome</hi> doubted not to denounce it accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed; but what seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him I do not care. I call that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible which never was, and which God
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:94200:45"/>hath decreed that it never shall be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vertuous doctrin!</hi> if the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be impossible, and that God hath decreed them so; <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo tenetur ad impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibile.</hi> Alas! we are of our selves too prone to take an allowance of sin, without this licence from Mr. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:94200:45"/>
            <p>To be short, the Church of God may and ought to reform themselves, in case of error or corruption of manners; but if once we admit others to do it, unauthorized or unsent, we open a wide door to all Sects and Heresies: and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other consequence is, we shall rest no where, but be tossed to and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:94200:46"/>fro (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> speaks) and carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with every wind of doctrin, with the various Lights of all Pretenders. This, one would think, hath been apparent enough in the experience of our Age: for fancy (commonly call'd rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son) when once broke loose from Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and from its Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:94200:46"/>runs forward it sees not whither, and knows not where to stop it self.</p>
            <p>Not that we deny our need of Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this world of Imperfection: but we give heed to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition of our bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Saviour, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.1. <hi>Verily I say unto you, he that enters not by
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:94200:47"/>the door into the Sheepfold, but climb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up some other way, the same is a thief and a robber.</hi> Not entring in at the door signifies entring without any Authority, either ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, when the Doctrins are new and strange; or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, when they are already known and confest. That
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:94200:47"/>the Liturgy and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of our Church are supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and Idolatrous, is to us very strange doctrin.</p>
            <p>Now let it be granted, for the sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression of Idolatry, in case the Church will not do her office, that it is lawful for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny unauthorized per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons (such as <hi>Knox,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:94200:48"/>&amp;c.</hi>) to take upon them to reform what they think amiss; there can be no suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient cause given (saith Bishop <hi>Sander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi>) why by the same reason, &amp; by the same grounds, <q>they may not take upon them to make Laws, raise Forces, administer Justice, execute Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors, (Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants)
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:94200:48"/>or do any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate should do, in case the Magistrate slack to do his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: which if it were once granted (as granted it must be, in case your Presbyterian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation be justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable) every wise man seeth, the end can be no other but
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:94200:49"/>vast Anarchy and confusion: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon must una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably follow the speedy subversion both of Religion and State. <hi>Second Sermon ad Clerum on Rom.</hi> 3.8.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This is our present case: You an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>authorised person, pretending to no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary things,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:94200:49"/>say all things are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miss: The Church is of opinion, yea, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded in her consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that you do all things amiss; who shall be Judg? the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> alas! the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is a Law; and no Law can ever pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce either for one or t'other, but in the mouth of some Judg. The Scripture must
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:94200:50"/>be Judg, say the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents,</hi> to avoid the Censures of your <hi>Kirk:</hi> what Schisma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick shall ever be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed, that must be tried by a law, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of himself must be the <hi>Interpreter?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From all these pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises I perswade my self your Ancestors were no Prophets sent from God, but
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:94200:50"/>intruded themselves on the office of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; or (as the Prophet speaks) they followed their own spirits, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied out of their own hearts. <hi>I have not sent these Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, yet they ran; I have not spoken to them, yet they prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sied; therefore they shall not profit this
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:94200:51"/>people at all,</hi> Jer. 23.21, 32.</p>
            <p>To add one word more; consider all the Prophets mentioned in holy Scripture, <hi>Samuel, Elias, Isaiah, Jeremy, Hosea, &amp;c.</hi> at the beginning of whose Prophecies (that the world might understand their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Mission) it is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sually declared how
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:94200:51"/>and in what manner they receiv'd it. <hi>Isa.</hi> 6. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 1. so as their Authority was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed, when the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of their Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies was little regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Some of them were qualified extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily with the power of Miracles, Prediction of future and publick events. Others had the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:94200:52"/>licence from the Schools of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</p>
            <p>In the new Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, our blessed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, beside the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal excellency of their Doctrin, gave the world sufficient external evidence that they were persons sent from God: And whereas you say that
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:94200:52"/>you preach no other Doctrin than that of Christ and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, it is the answer of Socinians, Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents, &amp;c. persons no less sober and learned than your selves; and (flatter not your self) will serve every mans turn as well as yours. I am not now disputing whether you preach
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:94200:53"/>the Doctrin of Christ and his Apostles; but by what Authority do you preach the Doctrin of <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian?</hi> until this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, we understand no foundation of your <hi>Kirk,</hi> beside your own perswasion; w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> can be no better than any mans else that is as strongly perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the contrary.</p>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:94200:53"/>
            <p>But in the last place, cannot you ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stify your selves by the sobriety and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of your lives? by the loyalty of your Actions? it is a great <hi>Controversie,</hi> and I shall not take upon me to pronounce my own sence of it: But you have heard of King <hi>James</hi> his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in the matter.
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:94200:54"/>
               <hi>Ego a Puritanis non solum a nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitate conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuo vexatus fui,
<note place="margin">In Praefatione Monitoria.</note> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum etiam in ipso ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris utero propemodum extinctus, antequam in lucem editus fui.</hi> The Puritans (saith he) have vexed me not only since my birth, but before, they had almost destroyed me in my Mothers womb.</p>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:94200:54"/>
            <p>And his Son the blessed K. <hi>Charles</hi> the First, from a certain intimate Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with your Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, writes thus to our present Soveraign K. <hi>Charles</hi> the 2. <q>If ever need of them, or must you stand in stand to their curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, you are undone; you may never ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect less of loyalty,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:94200:55"/>justice, or humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, then from those who engage into re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Rebellion; under the Colours of piety, ambitious Policies, march, not only with greatest security, but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plause as to the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulace: you may hear from them <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> voice, but you shall feel they have
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:94200:55"/>
                  <hi>Esaus</hi> hands.</q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc> in non-Latin alphabet </desc>
               </gap>. <hi>chap.</hi> 27.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Lutheran</hi> Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches at this day speak no otherwise of your <hi>Party:</hi> for instance, let us hear <hi>Waltherus,</hi> a late <hi>Lutheran</hi> Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintendent, speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his <hi>Harmonia Biblica</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with the <hi>Calvinists.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Impressa No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimbergae an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1654. <hi>pag.</hi> 1106.</note>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:94200:56"/>Before this can be, <hi>rgenda sunt</hi> (saith he) <hi>tres admonitiones valde necessariae. Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, ut mentiendi libi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem deponant</hi> Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinistae. <hi>Secunda, ut turbulentis &amp; sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>osis machinationibus (ex quibus hactenus quasi compacti esse to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, non nobis magis quam orbi Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum universo visi
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:94200:56"/>sunt) valedicentes, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci publicae favere, &amp; pietatis cultumintran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillo exercere sata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, &amp;c.</hi> In order to this reconciliation, we must desire the <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists</hi> (saith he) to grant us three things; First, that they leave off their humour of lying: The second, that abandoning their turbulent and sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:94200:57"/>Machinations (for hitherto they seem to be compacted of nothing else, I appeal to all the Christian World) they would incline to the publick Peace; and at length serve God in quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. The Third, That they would sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the World by some publick Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, which of their
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:94200:57"/>Errors, Blasphemies, and Corruptions of the Scripture they are resolved to forgo; <hi>Donec nihil horum fit ab ipsis, intra gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium pacis &amp; frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis, a nobis plane nec possunt nec debent admitti:</hi> Whilst they will do nothing of all this, in plain terms (saith he) we neither can nor ought
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:94200:58"/>to admit them as Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren.</p>
            <p>You may consult <hi>Waltherus,</hi> and see much more to this purpose, <hi>Harm. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blica, Pag.</hi> 1102, 1103. 1104. w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> is the sence of all the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Churches at this day.</p>
            <p>Thus have I given you the reasons of my dissatisfaction concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Validity of
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:94200:58"/>your <hi>Presbyterian Mission.</hi> And I must confess that I have here expressed only some wishes, not any hopes of convincing you; all my expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation is, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps some unpreju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced Persons will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that your <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Kirk</hi> hath no advantage, in point of a solid Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:94200:59"/>over <hi>Independents, Anabaptists,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The sum of what hath been said is this; 'tis not true Doctrine alone without exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and lawfull <hi>Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,</hi> that makes a Preacher of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel. Your <hi>Commission</hi> therefore must ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, ere you can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige any prudent Persons to be your
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:94200:59"/>Hearers; to derive it from <hi>Prelates,</hi> is to ruin your selves; for that is to confess the Authority of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops; if Episcopal <hi>Mission</hi> be valid (which meer necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty forces you to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess) then have our <hi>Ministers</hi> a good Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to Preach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst your <hi>Kirk.</hi> This you would fain
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:94200:60"/>evade, by saying it is valid as to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, but not as to Circumstances; and I would as fain know who gave you power to alter it as to Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances? all this confirms what your Country-man <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi> says in his late Dialogue between a Conformist &amp; Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformist; <hi>Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:94200:60"/>is the very soul of the Kirk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If instead of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent answer to all this Discourse, you shall please to pass your censure on the Author, and say he is some <hi>Papist,</hi> I must reply to you in the words of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Bishop <hi>Sander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> concerning the Puritan Preachers:</p>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:94200:61"/>
            <p>
               <q>Some of them, especially such as betake themselves to Preaching be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and have not the leisure and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to look much into Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versies, understand very little of the true state of the question betwixt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and us; and yet to
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:94200:61"/>shew their zeal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>against Popery, are forward enough to be medling with it in the Pulpit, but with so much weakness and impertinency, that they leave the question worse than the found it, and the Hearer, if he brought any doubts with him, to go from Sermon more
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:94200:62"/>dissatisfied than he came. <hi>Preface to</hi> 14 <hi>Sermons printed an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1657.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In fine, as you have no true Mission to preach the Gospel, so am I satisfied it is not the Gospel you teach, but somewhat else instead of it. Give me leave to parallel the Maxims of the <hi>Gospel</hi> with those of
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:94200:62"/>your <hi>Party.</hi> First the Maxims of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel are these.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Love your enemies. Do good to them that hate you, and despite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully use you. Render to no man evil for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. Speak evil of no man. If ye suffer for righteousness sake hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py are ye. Let no man suffer as a busie body in other mens matters.
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:94200:63"/>Submit your selves to every Ordinance of man for the Lords sake, whether it be to the King as supreme, or unto Governors as unto them that are sent by him. As free, and not using your liberty for a Cloak of malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness. Servants be subject to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters with all fear, not only to the good and
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:94200:63"/>gentle, but also to the froward. For what glory is it, if when ye be buffetted for your faults, ye take it pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, but if when ye do well and suffer for it, this is acceptable with God,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.20. <hi>Be perfect, be of one mind. Live in Peace. Be not wise in your own conceits; that is, fancy not your selves
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:94200:64"/>more enlightned than others that have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the same Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity. What? came the word of God out from you, or came it unto you alone?</hi> 1 Cor. 14.36. <hi>I beseech you by the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that ye all speak the same thing</hi> (observe this) <hi>and that there be no schisms among you;
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:94200:64"/>but that ye be perfectly joyned together in the same mind and in the same judgment,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.10. <hi>Obey them that have the rule over you, and submit your selves. They that do other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, serve not the Lord Jesus Christ but their own belly;</hi> that is, their own interest. It is better to be the first, second, or third
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:94200:65"/>man in a Schism, than the fortieth, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the hundreth man, in the great bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Church.</p>
            <p>Let us now hear your Doctrins, I mean your <hi>Characteristical</hi> ones of your Party.</p>
            <p>It is lawful to raise defensive Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the King; as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serted by your late Book entituled <hi>Jus
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:94200:65"/>Populi vindicatum.</hi> The Persons of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces may be resisted, though not their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. Princes may be deposed and put to death in case of tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny;
<note place="margin">See <hi>Rutherford Lex Rex.</hi>
               </note> of which tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the People (vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and divided as they are) must be Judges. The King is <hi>singulis major,</hi> but <hi>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niversis
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:94200:66"/>minor.</hi> The People may enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Covenant for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, without consent of the King. If Magistrates (saith your Confession of Faith, <hi>chap.</hi> 31.) be open enemies to the Presbyterian Church, the Ministers of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, by virtue of their office, with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fit Persons may
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:94200:66"/>meet in their Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies. We are to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguish betwixt the Kings personal and politick capacity: All humane Laws must bend to the Law of necessity. <hi>Adeo Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus atque Principi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus insita est quasi perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um &amp; verna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum malum arrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> saith <hi>Calvin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Comment. in Sencae li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum</hi> 1. <hi>de Clementia.</hi>
               </note> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogance
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:94200:67"/>is a vice al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most perpetual and natural to Kings.</p>
            <p>These are some of your Evangelical do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrins. Besides, I have been sometimes no negligent Hearer of your Sermons, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting when you would inform me di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctly and material<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of my duty to God, to my Prince,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:94200:67"/>or to my Neighbour; but this I might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect long enough.</p>
            <p>Truly, Christ and his Apostles did not cant after your man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner about Free grace and Priviledges of the Godly and get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting an interest in Christ, without per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swading the necessity of keeping his <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments. Ye are
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:94200:68"/>my friends</hi> (saith he) <hi>if ye do whatsoever I command you,</hi> Joh. 15, 14. The sum of the <hi>Gospel</hi> is this, that whereas in <hi>Adam</hi> we lost a Terrestrial Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radise, our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ the second <hi>Adam</hi> came into the world to restore us to a Celestial: but how restore us? by turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away every one of
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:94200:68"/>us from his iniquities, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.26. that God for Christs sake will remember our sins no more, provided we become new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: and that it is idle to expect the one without the other; for Christ is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of eternal Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to them that O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.9. What this New crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:94200:69"/>is, your manner is to express with so much verbosity and oddness of language, besides impertinency, that your <hi>Auditors</hi> can never be the wiser except in their own conceits; whereas the Scripture gives us to understand it in very few, and those very plain words. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.19. with <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.15.</p>
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:94200:69"/>
            <p>The Creed, the Lords Prayer, the ten Commandments, and the Sacraments, are the entire con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of all that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction necessary to Salvation, which lies dispersed in the body of the Scriptures. This your People not understanding (like those silly wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men St. <hi>Paul</hi> speaks
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:94200:70"/>of) are always learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and never able to come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the Truth, heaping to themselves Teachers, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But (you will say) does not our <hi>Kirk</hi> expound the <hi>Creed?</hi> I answer no, not in your shorter Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chism, where its set down with much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do at the later end
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:94200:70"/>without explanation; to intimate what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem you would have us put upon it.</p>
            <p>The best of your Sermons (Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> for instance) if seriously considered, may very well serve to raise the Affections of their Hearers, but never settle their Understandings: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed we are led into a
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:94200:71"/>Wilderness by your Prayers, and a Laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth by your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. The <hi>Lord Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con</hi> observ'd it long ago, that your dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses (considering the tone and accent wherein they are ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered) are sometimes very powerful to bring sinners to the question what shall we do to be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved?
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:94200:71"/>but seldom or never tell us what. To my understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all your Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is to as much pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, as if a <hi>Judg,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of informing the Jury particularly and materially what our Laws forbid and what they require, should only affect to entertain them with a general Harangue
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:94200:72"/>of the excellency of <hi>Law.</hi> To tell your Auditors plainly and materially what they have to do, would, I confess, conduce but little to your designs. Fear God and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church. Do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all other men as
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:94200:72"/>you would they should do unto you. This is <hi>Pagan</hi> mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and (if the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple understood it) would spoil your pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses of supplanting the present establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Church: though for want of such mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Preaching, hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your <hi>Party</hi> have had the luck to be as little remarked for
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:94200:73"/>their honest dealing, and less, perhaps, than other <hi>Sects.</hi> O but you preach against the Prophaneness, Drunkenness, and Whoredom of the Age! yes, I know it very well: and I also understand to preach against nothing else but the prophaneness of the <hi>Times,</hi> is very convenient for your
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:94200:73"/>designs: 'tis a <hi>Theam</hi> your People love to hear of, rather than of Envy, Malice, Lying, Sedition, Pharisaical pride, and such like infirmities of the Saints. There are (you know) sins of malevolence as well as sins of appetite; in the latter a man plays the Beast; but in the former he plays
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:94200:74"/>the Devil. In a word, the Christian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion as delivered by our blessed Saviour and his Apostles, hath very much in it to oblige <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Infidels:</hi> but as for your Sermons 'tis a Miracle to me, if ever they oblige, I do not say Infidels, but any ingenious Christians. Flatter
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:94200:74"/>not your selves; the world can never be amended by your Preaching; for in the same Sermon whilst you are beating down Prophaneness, you slily encourage the popular humours of Inconstancy, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, Pride, Censori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness, Sedition, &amp;c. To say nothing of your impertinent ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:94200:75"/>of <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> Texts, especially these following; <hi>Ye are bought with a price, be not ye the servants of men,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.23. <hi>Stand fast in the liberty wherewith Christ hath made you free,</hi> Gal. 5.1. <hi>Why as though living in the world are ye subject to Ordinances,</hi> Col. 2.20. <hi>In vain do ye
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:94200:75"/>worship me, teaching for doctrins the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of men,</hi> Mar. 7.7. <hi>The Kings of the Gentiles exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise Lordship over them, but it shall not be so among you. O Father, thou hast hid these things from the wise and prudent, and hast revealed them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Babes.</hi> With these and other places of
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:94200:76"/>Scripture perverted from their true mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, you triumph, as you imagine, over the Ceremonies and Government of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But truly when a man considers it seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously, other than po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular and wretched conceptions cannot be expected from the Ministers of your
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:94200:76"/>
               <hi>Kirk,</hi> who being ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally of the lowest of the People of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and their means of education very slender, are necessita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (for all their <hi>try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als</hi> as you call it) to set up with very little Acquaintance either of <hi>Men</hi> or Books that are considerable. This being their case, no wonder if their
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:94200:77"/>
               <hi>Notions</hi> are so suita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and level with the Fancies of some Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as Women, Tradesmen, Shop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers, Malecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, which compose the <hi>main</hi> of their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors. This sort of people (many of them) conscious to themselves of their escapes in point of <hi>vertuous dealing,</hi> are
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:94200:77"/>very much obliged by your Sermons of Free grace, Justification by Faith alone; Impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibility of keeping the Commandments, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute Promises, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And so much for your Mission and your Doctrin. Let us now, if you please, confer a few words a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout some other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and so conclude.</p>
            <pb n="148" facs="tcp:94200:78"/>
            <p>First, concerning that Principle of yours, That nothing is to be done about the Worship and Service of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out express warrant in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: And I pray inform us, where has our blessed Saviour or his Apostles ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed a <hi>Directory</hi> for Publick Prayer?
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:94200:78"/>hath the spirit any need of a <hi>Directory?</hi> what divine warrant can you produce for your singing to God in a set Form, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusing to pray in a set Form? for speaking to him your sudden and extemporary thoughts, but speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the People with a studied and composed Sermon?
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:94200:79"/>in which of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels are to be found those three significant Ceremonies required at the taking your So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant? first that we must be Uncovered; secondly, that we must Stand up; third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with our Right hand lift up bare? what express Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture have you for
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:94200:79"/>your Form of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Penance called the Stool of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance? for your Clas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and Synods? your shifting of <hi>Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors?</hi> or indeed for any thing you do in opposition to the present established <hi>Church?</hi> This Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of yours (as hath been already observ'd by the Friendly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate)
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:94200:80"/>makes that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful which the Scripture allows; in which we find many holy men doing those things (without any censure) in Gods Worship which he had no where com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded. For instance, what commandment had <hi>David</hi> for his design of building a Temple? or <hi>Solomon</hi>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:94200:80"/>for keeping a Feast of Seaven days for the Dedication of the Altar? for erecting an Altar to be as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended by steps? ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly forbidden in the 20. of <hi>Exodus</hi> ver. 26. <hi>Thou shalt not go up by steps un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mine Altar.</hi> What warrant had <hi>Hezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> for continuing the Feast of unleavened
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:94200:81"/>bread seaven days longer than the time appointed by the Law? 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 30.23. If you say that all these things possibly were warranted, though not by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but now Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture warrant is neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary, since extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary inspirations are ceas'd: I pray tell us what Scripture have
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:94200:81"/>you for this very As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sertion, that extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Inspirations are ceas'd? if this be true, what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary gifts of your Ancestors, <hi>Calvin, Knox, Goodman,</hi> &amp;c. for ordinary <hi>Mission</hi> they had none. In a word this principle of yours makes the Worship of God
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:94200:82"/>impossible; the Time, the, Place, the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture, in which it shall be performed being no where appointed. Do not <hi>Anabaptists</hi> and <hi>Quakers</hi> retort it on your selves? the one demanding ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press Scripture for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants Baptism, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for standing in a Pulpit; for preaching upon a Text, and
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:94200:82"/>that by an Hour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glass, stinting the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> 'Tis not conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences nor evident deductions they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, but express <hi>Scripture:</hi> for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else will content you in the matter of Liturgy and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</p>
            <p>Another thing I would intreat you to reflect upon, is the
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:94200:83"/>reason of your dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure at the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Revenues and Encouragements of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> That which dissenters, <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, Anabaptists,</hi> (if I understand them aright) would be at, is this, that the <hi>Clergie</hi> be reduced to their primitive poverty and dependence on
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:94200:83"/>the People: and, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, <hi>Judas</hi> hath ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well expressed their sense, <hi>John</hi> 12.4. <hi>To what purpose is all this waste of precious ointment on the feet of Christ? might it not have been sold for three hundred pence and given to the poor? This he said, not that he cared for the poor, but because he had the
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:94200:84"/>bag and was a Thief.</hi> They consider not, how many vertues there are requisite in a Church-man, which can have no place in the house of scarsity; how little exemplary charity, temperance, or humility can be expected from a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Estate, that we cannot say he is a temperate man, who
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:94200:84"/>is so, having scarcely wherewithal to satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his thirst; or an humble person whose fortune gives him small temptation to be proud: are not all Christians under the same obligations of humility and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Riches as the Clergy? Lay not up for your selves treasures upon earth,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:94200:85"/>was said to all: and is it not true in experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that the pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Priests must be attended with igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranee or very slender knowledge besides contempt? the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessities of our bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Saviour and his Apostles upon earth were supplied by Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, and therefore their case and ours
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:94200:85"/>not the same. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever Sectaries may think of the Church Revenues, the <hi>Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical</hi> Maintenance ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self was far more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable. Give me leave to recommend to your considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on those excellent words of K. <hi>Charles</hi> the First <q>The Conclusion of
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc> in non-Latin alphabet </desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>chap.</hi> 14.</note>
                  <pb n="164" facs="tcp:94200:86"/>the War makes it evident, that the main Reformation intended was the robbing the Church of its Lands, and the abasing of Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy into Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery: but no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity shall ever, I hope, drive me or mine to invade or sell the Priests Lands, which even
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:94200:86"/>
                  <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s divinity ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred to do: if the Poverty of <hi>Scotland</hi> might, yet the Plenty of <hi>England</hi> cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse the envy and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine of the Church-Lands. The next work will be <hi>Jeroboams</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, consecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the meanest of the People to be Priests in Israel, to serve those Golden Calves who have enriched them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves by the Churches Patrimony.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, Deceive not your
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:94200:87"/>self with the pleasant fancy, that if once <hi>Bishops</hi> were put down, their <hi>Lands</hi> will be vested on you and your Brethren.</p>
            <p>Lastly, be pleased to reflect on your displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure at the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Some of you are for no Forms at all; others are for Liturgy, but it must be reformed.</p>
            <p>In the History of the Reign of Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> this passage is observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Four <hi>Classes</hi> of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians complained of
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:94200:87"/>the Liturgy to the Lord <hi>Burleigh,</hi> then Secretary of State;
<note place="margin">About the year 1585.</note> his Lordship bad them go and make a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: Whereupon the first <hi>Classis</hi> went and framed a new one, somewhat near that of <hi>Geneva.</hi> This the second <hi>Classis</hi> dislikes, and alters in six hundred particulars; which alteration was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted against by the third <hi>Classis;</hi> and what the third resolved upon, the fourth would not consent to. Thus your
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:94200:88"/>
               <hi>Party</hi> expect a satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on about the Worship of God, which is impossible to be given you.</p>
            <p>As to your praying by the Spirit, there is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>doubt</hi> in it, which hitherto none of you would do us the kindness to resolve: either you mean praying by the Spirit of God, or by your own spirits: If you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the words and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of your Prayer by the dictate of the holy Spirit, then are your prayers as much the word of God
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:94200:88"/>as any of <hi>Davids</hi> Psalms, or as any part of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and being written from your mouths, may become Canonical Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: If by praying with the Spirit, you only mean that you are inspired with devout affections, then there is nothing in your prayers, but what others may pretend to as well as your selves. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you cannot be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that praying by the spirit in the <hi>Scripture</hi> sense is praying in an unknown tongue. <hi>I will pray with
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:94200:89"/>the spirit</hi> (saith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle) <hi>and will pray with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding also. If I pray in an unknown tongue, my spirit prayeth, but my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding is unfruitful,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.15. Thus you mistake the sense of Scripture. In brief, since you do not pretend to entertain your people with immediate inspira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, you oblige them to a <hi>service</hi> they know not what; to offer up pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers whereof they know not a syllable, nor your self neither, before you
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:94200:89"/>begin: if you know them before hand either for matter or words, then they cannot be <hi>extempore,</hi> as you would have the People believe. Perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture the reason why the People fancy your prayers, is, their variety: they love not to go where they must be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies entertained with the same expressions: but if the sense of our own infirmities (which are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the same) cannot oblige us to pray, why should a set of <hi>new</hi> words
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:94200:90"/>do it? They that are for new <hi>words</hi> will at last have new <hi>things,</hi> or worse than nothing, saith Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in his <hi>Cure of Church-Divisions, p.</hi> 184. <hi>third Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I conclude with the words of the blessed Martyr King <hi>Charles</hi> the First, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc> in non-Latin alphabet </desc>
               </gap>. chap. 16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Some men are so impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent not to use in all their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions their own invention and gifts, that they wholly cast away and contemn the Lords Prayer. I ever thought that the proud ostentation of mens
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:94200:90"/>own abilities for invention, and the vain affectation of variety for expressions in Publick Prayer, merits a greater brand of sin, than that which they call coldness or barreness: Nor are men in those Novelties less sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to formal and superfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial tempers (as to their hearts) than in the use of constant Forms, where not the Words but mens Hearts are too blame. I make no doubt but a man may be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry formal in the most extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary variety, and very fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vently devout in the most
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:94200:91"/>wonted expressions. Nor is God more a God of vuriety than of constancy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Novelty in Religion may give (saith he) some short flashes of content to the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar People, who are taken with every new change as children with Babies, very much, but not very long.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:94200:91"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>